1990年四月，美国的发现号航天飞机升空
In April of 1990 the American space shuttle Discovery launched up from the Earth
将哈勃太空望远镜送到航天飞机从未到达过的高度
into a higher orbit than ever before to deploy a special payload the Hubble Space Telescope
那个高度，大气层几乎是最稀薄的
Above even the thinnest parts of the atmosphere
这使得哈勃能够清晰地看到遥远的恒星与星系
Hubble would be able to see far-off stars and galaxies without distortion
让我们能看到宇宙更遥远的过去
and expand our understanding of the distant past
至少原计划是这样
or at least that was the plan
但到了六月，人们证实哈勃出现了大问题
But by June it was clear there was something a very wrong
望远镜的主镜竟然无法准确对焦
The telescope with one of the most perfectly round mirrors couldn't focus properly
太空中首个最先进的宇宙观测平台成了近视眼
Apparently the first great space observatory was short sighted
哈勃直径2.5米(8英尺2英寸)的主镜形状出现了偏差
Hubble's two and a half meter or 8'2" foot mirror was rendered incapable by an error in its shape
偏差大概是头发直径的五分之一(2.2微米)
less than one fiftieth of the width of a human hair
左侧为正确打磨的镜子 右侧为出现球面像差的镜子
这个偏差术语叫“球面像差”
The primary mirror suffered from what is known as spherical aberration
这在业余爱好者制造的简易望远镜中很常见
more often found in sloppily made amateur telescope projects
但不应该出现在造价上百万美元的太空望远镜上
not multi-million dollar space telescopes
但这个偏差在主镜制造中存在了整整十年
However this was a problem almost a decade in the making
NASA找珀金埃尔默公司制造哈勃望远镜的光学组件与精确制导系统
NASA had contracted the private firm Perkin-Elmer to make Hubble's optical assembly and the fine guidance system
主镜的制造开始于1979年，完成于1981年
Construction of the primary mirror began in 1979 and was completed in 1981
但其间整个项目其实如履薄冰
but during these years the whole project was under threat
经费爆炸，交付日期各种咕
costs were rising and the scheduled to deliver on time was slipping
甲方爸爸NASA逼迫珀金埃尔默公司，要么抓紧干要么滚犊子
NASA put the heat on the management of Perkin-Elmer pushing them to keep up with the schedule or loose for contract
在幕后，主镜的打磨与测试也在进行中
Behind-the-scenes, the polishing and testing of the primary mirror was underway
由于哈勃的镜面是非球面的
Because Hubble's mirror was an aspherical design
因此需要一种叫“零校正器”的特殊仪器来精确检查打磨质量
it required special apparatus to check its quality known as a null corrector
为此，珀金埃尔默还自制了一台高精零校正器(RNC)
Perkin-Elmer even designed their own high specification reflective null corrector or RNC
测试标准可达一微米(千分之一毫米)，以满足太空望远镜的精度需求
to test the exact standard of one micrometer or 1/1000 of a millimeter as required for the Space Telescope
RNC呈圆柱体，76厘米(2.5英尺)高，半米宽(1.5英尺)
The RNC was a cylinder, 76 centimeters, 2.5 feet high and about half a meter or 1.5 feet wide
其内部，两面镜子和一块透镜被安排的明明白白
Inside, two mirrors and a lens were arranged
从而制造波阵面，射向下方的哈勃主镜
to create a wavefront on the Hubble primary mirror below
如果主镜打磨正确，得到的应该是左图没有外轮廓的线条
If the mirror was fabricated perfectly, this wavefront would show no contour lines
“‘零’校正器”因此得名
hence the a null in the instruments name
该设备得到认可后，人们花了两周把它放在特制房间内的一个塔顶上
The apparatus was approved and set up on a tower in a dedicated room, a process that took two weeks
RNC的位置由一根因瓦合金棒测量得到
The position of the RNC's lens was measured by an Invar Rod
该测量棒由镍钢合金组成，膨胀系数随温度变化极小，得名“不变钢”
a precision made and measured rod of nickel iron alloy named for its invariability
invariability，不变性
该测量棒由镍钢合金组成，膨胀系数随温度变化极小，得名“不变钢”
specifically low expansion under different temperatures
如果测量棒长度改变不到一毫米，测量结果也会出错
If the length of this rod varied by even a fraction of a millimeter the test measurements would be wrong
从而导致主镜打磨出现偏差
and the mirror would be ground to a wrong shape
当技术人员降低RNC中的透镜时，他们发现根本装不进去
As the technicians lowered the lens of the RNC into position, they noticed they couldn't get it all to fit together
测量棒长了一毫米多
The Invar Rod stuck out by just over a millimeter
测量棒的两端是打磨过的弧面
The ends of the Invar rod were rounded and polished
因为定位系统使用的是光干涉测量而不是机械测量
because the positioning system used a light interferometer rather than a mechanical measurement
这个过程中需要一束会聚光在测量棒末端反射回来
As part of this process a focused beam of light was reflected off the end of the Invar rod
为了保证会聚光刚好在测量棒末端中心反射
To make sure that it was focused exactly on the center of a rod end
测量棒两端各装有一个适配帽
field caps were fitted to hold the rods in position laterally
其中间有小孔，保证会聚光能刚好射在测量棒末端中心处
these caps had a hole in the center to allow the focus beams hit the rod end
而适配帽一圈则是不反光的
and a non-reflective surface coating around it
在某一时刻，其中一个适配帽上不反光的部分
At some point, a small section of this non-reflective coating
从中间剥落了一小块
on one of the field caps was chipped off around the center hole
而技术人员设定会聚光位置时
When the technician was setting up the focused beam
他得到的是适配帽上剥落部分的反射光线
he got a reflection from the chipped area of the endcap instead of the rod end
造成测量棒位置出现1.3毫米的误差
which caused a 1.3 millimeter misplacing of the Invar rod
他们没有花时间调查RNC组装后和测量棒不适配
Rather than wasting time investigating why the assembly didn't match the Invar Rod
而是找三个垫圈硬塞进支架里去支撑透镜
the crew found three metal spacers and squeezed them into the bracket holding the lens
这样测量棒就能塞进去啦~
so now it agreed with the measuring rod
然后RNC就再没动过，防止干扰到主镜的微调
Then the RNC was left in place so as not to disturb its supposedly fine calibration
RNC组装上的疏忽导致主镜打磨精确度出现问题
The result of this oversight in the assembly of the RNC would lead to the mirror being precisely polished
其误差超过了容忍限度的十倍
but with an error ten times greater than the specified tolerance
就这样，整个团队花了九个月打磨主镜
Every day for 9 months the crew polished the primary mirror
定期把主镜送到零校正器下观察还要打磨多久
periodically moving it on its tracks to the null corrector to see how much closer they were to the final shape
最终RNC给出了刚刚提到的“零”的结果
At the end of the long process the RNC gave a Null result
于是这块主镜就被打磨到“完美”了
at last the so-called perfect mirror was finished
为了测试主镜形状，他们还用另外一个简易的零校正器
To verify the mirror shape another test was carried out using a cruder refractive Null corrector
却给出了不同的结果
but this test gave a different result
这次测试尽管显示哈勃主镜有缺陷
This time it appears as though the Hubble's mirror had a flaw
但测试用的零校正器并没有经过球面像差测试
But as the refractive null corrector had not been certified for testing against spherical aberration
于是人们并没有在意这个结果
the result was discounted
所以结果是，主镜的误差其实早就被发现了，但没人在意
The fault had been found but it had been ignored
更惨的是，人们没有深入调查这两次测试结果上的出入
and moreover the discrepancy between the two tests had not been investigated further
也没人在维修记录上提到之前说的三个垫圈
and the written documentation of the fix with the spacers was also misplaced
后来挑战者号航天飞机出事，任务延期，镜面封存了四年
Over the four years that the mirror was stored due to delays because of the Challenger shuttle disaster
几个大学要求拿出来亲自测试一下主镜，但不了了之
several universities requested permission to test the mirror and all were turned down
因为制造商珀金埃尔默对他们自己的测试过程蜜汁自信
because the manufacturers were confident about their own testing procedures
于是十年后，这架造价15亿美元的太空望远镜就这样带病上天了
A decade later the one and a half billion dollar Space Telescope was high above the earth with a flawed mirror
柯达那边其实有一个完美的备份主镜
There was a perfect backup mirror that had been made by Kodak
但望远镜已经上天，不可能在轨更换主镜
but it would have been impossible to replace the mirror once in orbit
把它运回地球重装也太浪费时间浪费钱
and too time-consuming and expensive to bring the Hubble back to earth of refitting
所以在1993年，人们执行了一次伟大而昂贵的航天飞机任务，其间进行五次太空行走
So in 1993, an ambitious and expensive shuttle mission with five spacewalks
将修正用的光学组件安装在哈勃的副镜上，成功解决了问题
managed to install corrective optics on the secondary mirror to fix the problem
当哈勃的问题发现以后
When the cause of Hubble's trouble was eventually found
珀金埃尔默同意支付1500万美元罚金
Perkin-Elmer agreed to pay a fine of $15 million dollars
以此来避免政府进一步的起诉
thereby avoiding a lawsuit by the government
珀金埃尔默和NASA也因对制造过程的品控的不负责
Both Perkin-Elmer and NASA were heavily criticised for not picking up on the quality control issues
和依靠单一设备进行测试的行为而被批判一番
and relying upon a single test instrument
哈勃至今仍在服役，几十年中维护了几次
Hubble is still in operation today and has been updated over the years
预计会继续服役到2028到2040年
And it's expected that it will be in operation until between 2028 and 2040
如果再没其它飞行器给它加燃料续命，大气阻力会让它落回地球
when the natural decay its orbits will bring it back to earth if it is not reboosted into a higher orbit
在那之前它仍会给人类带来
Until then it will continue to provide mankind with
无数既有科学价值、又美轮美奂的宇宙图片
some of the most scientifically useful and inspirational views of our universe to date
所以感谢观看啦，这期这件衣服
So thanks for watching and I just like to say that this episode shirt
在下面这商店有卖
was the Penny Dot Lane Retro Mod Polka dot by madcap England and it's available at
这衣服起码让视频大了几十兆
at Atomretro with world shipping from here in the UK
YouTuber频道“Curious Droid”，还有patreon和非死不可群组
Don't forget we also have the curious droid Facebook page and group
可以去那提建议
where you can suggest ideas for new videos between the channel page
字幕翻译给虫
And you can also translate any of the videos with the community contributions
感谢观看，记得点赞投币收藏分享关注
So as always thanks again for watching and please subscribe rate and share